Guide to the Clifton Ewing Hickok Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Clifton Ewing Hickok papers
1897-1915
1912-1915
WA MSS S-2762
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.34
(2 boxes) + 10 broadside folders
Correspondence, reports, charts, and maps created and compiled by Clifton Ewing Hickok related to water use and availability studies in southern California, as well as efforts by the Volcan Land and Water Company to sell its land and water rights to the city of San Diego, 1897-1915. The collection also includes reports and charts created by his business partner, William S. Post, and others, including Philip E. Harroun and Charles H. Lee.
Hickok, Clifton Ewing, 1880-1954
Harroun, Philip Embury, 1867-1947
Lee, Charles H. (Charles Hamilton), 1883-1967
Post, William S. (William Schuyler), 1871-1945
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Barry Lawrence Ruderman Antique Maps on the Thomas W. Streeter Fund, 2012.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Clifton Ewing Hickok (1880-1954)
Major Clifton Ewing Hickok (1880-1954) was a civil engineer and city manager of Alameda, California. He was born in St. Joseph, Missouri. He earned a Bachelor of Science in Civil Engineering from the University of California in 1908. In April 1912, he married visual artist Adelaide Valentine Cutler Hickok (1887-1987). They had a daughter, Beverly Hickok (born 1919). He worked as a civil engineer for several firms. From 1917 to 1921, he served as the city engineer for Alameda, California, except for years he served as an engineer with the United States Army during World War I, 1918-1919. In 1921, he became city manager of Alameda, California. He also served as the assistant Public Works Administrator of California during the Great Depression. In 1937, Hickok and his family moved to Berkeley, California.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, reports, charts, and maps created and compiled by Clifton Ewing Hickok related to water use and availability studies in southern California, as well as efforts by the Volcan Land and Water Co. to sell its land and water rights to the city of San Diego, 1897-1915. The collection also includes reports and charts created by his business partner, William S. Post, and others, including Philip E. Harroun and Charles H. Lee.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Papers, 1897-circa 1915. II. Oversize Papers, 1913-1915.
Water resources development -- California -- San Diego; Water resources development -- California, Southern; Water-supply -- California -- San Diego; Water-supply -- California, Southern; Harroun, Philip Embury, 1867-1947; Hickok, Clifton Ewing, 1880-1954; Lee, Charles H. (Charles Hamilton), 1883-1967; Post, William S. (William Schuyler), 1871-1945; Volcan Land and Water Company (Calif.)
- Papers, 1897-circa 1915; Series I; 15
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Adams, Arthur L., San Francisco, California, letter to the Board of Town Trustees, Oceanside, California, 1897 March 16 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Letter serves as a report about the best means and cost for providing a water supply for Oceanside, California
    Wrapper title: Report on Oceanside Project by Arthur L. Adams
  - Southern California Mountain Water Company, Proposition of the Southern California Mountain Water Company to Sell a Portion of its System of Water Works to the City of San Diego, also to Lease Other Portions of its System of Water Works to the City of San Diego with the Option of Purchasing the Same, 1912 February 10 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Post, William S., Report on Water Supply of the Bernardo Rancho, 1913 April 19 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Lippincott, Joseph Barlow, letter to San Diego Chamber of Commerce, San Diego, California, 1913 August 21 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Letter serves as a report about a proposed bond issue for extensions and improvements to the municipal water system in San Diego, California
  - Post, William S., Report on Cottonwood System of the City of San Diego, 1914 January 31 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Hickok, Clifton Ewing, Letter to William S. Post, about a letter by Joseph Barlow Lippincott to the San Diego Chamber of Commerce, San Diego, California, 1914 March 23 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Related Archival Materials note
    Associated materials: see Lippincott, Joseph Barlow, letter to San Diego Chamber of Commerce, San Diego, California, Box 1, folder 4
    Letter accompanied by notes that reference the report by Lippincott
  - Harroun, Philip E., Report to the City of San Diego and the Volcan Land and Water Company on the Safe Net Yield Value Cost of Completed System and Cost of Water Delivered of the Properties of the Volcan Land and Water Company, 1914 August (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Post, William S., Notes from a September 5, 1914, letter by Philip E. Harroun, that summarizes cost of constructing the Warner Dam, Carroll Dam, and pipeline from Carroll Dam to San Diego, California, 1914 September (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Post, William S., and Clifton Ewing Hickok, Report of the Cost of Construction of Warner-Carroll-University Supply to the City of San Diego as Outlined in Offer of the Volcan Land and Water Company to the City of San Diego, Dated May 22, 1914, 1914 October 10 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Hickok, Clifton Ewing, Notes on Carroll Dam, circa 1914 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Lee, Charles H., Preliminary Statement to the Volcan Land and Water Co. of Physical Situation on San Luis Rey River Relative to Injunction Suit Brought by City of Oceanside and Others, 1915 January 9 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Hickok, Clifton Ewing, Notes on Charles Sumner Slichter, Field Measurements of the Rate of Movement of Underground Waters, United States Geological Survey, Water-Supply and Irrigation Paper; No. 140, 1905, circa 1915 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Taylor, A. Movement of Underground Water, circa 1915 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Hickok, Clifton Ewing, Notes on Dam No. 1, circa 1915 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Hickok, Clifton Ewing, Notes on dams, circa 1915 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    General note
    Dams include the Hume-Bennett Dam at Sanger, California; Big Meadows Dam in Mineral County, Colorado; Los Verjeles Dam in Yuba County, California; and Bear Valley Dam in Big Bear Valley, California
- Oversize Papers, 1913-1915; Series II; 5; 5 folders + 10 broadsides
  Arranged chronologically
  - Hickok, Clifton Ewing, Cuyamaca Water Co., Types of Structures Contemplated for Replacement, 1913 July (Box 3 (Broadside))
  - Hickok, Clifton Ewing, Volcan Land & Water Co., Mass Curve, Warner Reservoir (Based on Reservoir Half Full at Beginning), 1913 July 1 (Box 4 (Broadside))
  - Post, William S., Volcan Land & Water Co., Outlet Tower, Warner Reservoir, 1913 August 19 (Box 5 (Broadside))
  - Post, William S., Volcan Land & Water Co., Cut and Fill Curves for Standard Canal on Ground Slopes of from 0° to 30°, 1913 August 22 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Post, William S., Volcan Land & Water Co., Warner Dam, 1913 October 14 (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
    2 drawings
    One drawing has manuscript notes by Hickok
  - Post, William S., Volcan Land & Water Co., Chart Showing Comparative Costs of Flume Types on Steep Slopes, 1913 November 4 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Post, William S., Rainfall Charts, San Luis Rey River Drainage, San Ysabel River Drainage, circa 1913 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Hickok, Clifton Ewing, Volcan Land & Water Co., Warner Reservoir, Elevation Showing Formation Encountered in Outlet Tunnel, 1914 May 7 (Box 6 (Broadside))
  - Hickok, Clifton Ewing, Volcan Land & Water Co., Mass Curve, Pamo Reservoir, Includes 15500 Acre Feet per annum From Warner Reservoir, 1914 June 16 (Box 7 (Broadside))
  - Volcan Land & Water Co., Mass Curve Tabulations for Pamo and Sutherland Reservoirs (Combined), 1914 August (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Exhibit G, Plans of Types of Conduit Proposed Warner-Pamo Conduit of the Volcan Land and Water Company in the Cleveland National Forest, San Diego County, California, circa 1914 (Box 8 (Oversize Broadside))
    Manuscript notes by Hickok
  - Map that documents drainages, dams, reservoirs, and conduits in San Diego County., circa 1914 (Box 9 (Oversize Broadside))
    Map constructed from topographic maps drafted by Richard Urquhart Goode, A. P. Davis, L. C. Fletcher, Joseph Barlow Lippincott, and T. G. Gerdine, and printed by the United States Geological Survey. Maps include the San Luis Rey Quadrangle (1901) and Ramona Quadrangle (1903)
  - Hickok, Clifton Ewing, Cuyamaca Water Co., Mass Diagram for San Diego River & South Fork, Exclusive of Cuyamaca Combined with the Proposed Mountain Reservoirs at Diverting Dam, Tule, Cedar, Conejos, Poverty Gulch, and the Present Reservoirs at La Mesa, Murray Hill, Eucalyptus, for Period July 1st 1894 to July 1st 1914, 1915 March (Box 10 (Oversize Broadside))
  - Cuyamaca Water Company, Statistics of Undeveloped Reservoir Sites on San Diego River, 1915 March 17 (Box 11 (Broadside))
  - Post, William S., Volcan Land & Water Co., Carroll Reservoir Multiple Arch Dam Stress Sheet, 1915 May 28 (Box 12 (Broadside))